Preliminary Guide to the Bertha "B" Holt papers, 1940-2010
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Bertha "B" Holt papers 1940-2010
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Holt, Bertha B.
Extent: 3425 items 5.5 linear feet
Bertha "B" Holt is a longtime resident of Burlington, North Carolina. She was first appointed to the N.C. House of Representatives in 1975 and later won re-election eight times. Collection includes campaign materials; correspondence, 1977-2000s; and research materials from various bills and issues from Holt's career. Other files relate to Holt's activities, including the Women's Forum of North Carolina, North Carolina Legislative Women's Caucus; the State Council for Social Legislation; the Science and Technology Board; tribute dinners and awards; clippings; a scrapbooks; and other miscellaneous papers and letters. Acquired as part of the Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture.
RL.00567
Language: Materials in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
Gift, 2009 (2009-0097), 2.7 lin. ft.
Gift, 2010 (2010-0104), 1.3 lin. ft.
Gift, 2010 (2010-0192), 1.5 lin. ft.
Biographical / Historical Note
Bertha "B" Holt is a longtime resident of Burlington, North Carolina. She was first appointed to the N.C. House of Representatives in 1975 and later won re-election eight times.
Collection Overview
Accession (2009-0097) (1650 items; 2.7 lin. ft.; dated 1970s-2008) includes campaign materials; correspondence, 1977-2000s; and research materials from various bills and issues from Holt's career, including the ERA, marital rape, wine laws, the lottery, juvenile justice, nursing, health education, mental retardation, archaeology, domestic violence, hospice, and the Holocaust. Other files relate to Holt's legislative career, including the North Carolina Legislative Women's Caucus; the State Council for Social Legislation; tribute dinners and awards; and other miscellaneous papers and letters.
Accession (2010-0104) (750 items; 1.3 lin. ft.; dated 1970-2010) includes clippings; correspondence; subject and research files from issues such as churches, seatbelt and school bus safety, welfare, gun control, and wine; committee materials, including the Science and Technology Board; a scrapbook from 1973-1979; and other miscellaneous materials.
Accession (2010-0192) (1125 items; 1.5 lin. ft.; dated 1940-2007) includes subject and research files from issues such as healthcare, education, crime, and prisons; materials from the Equal Rights Amendment; files from various events that Holt attended, including the Center for Creative Leadership, the White House Conference on Aging (1981), and files from her membership in the Women's Forum of North Carolina. Also contains materials from her Episcopal Church activities.
Subject Headings
Holt, Bertha B.; Education -- North Carolina; Equal rights amendments -- North Carolina; Juvenile courts -- North Carolina; Law and ethics; Lottery tickets -- North Carolina; North Carolina; North Carolina. House of Representatives; Rape -- North Carolina; Sex discrimination against women; Wine -- North Carolina; Women's Forum of North Carolina; Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture
Contents of Collection
- Accession (2009-0097), 1970-2008, (3 boxes)
  Accession (2009-0097) (1650 items; 2.7 lin. ft.; dated 1970s-2008) includes campaign materials; correspondence, 1977-2000s; and research materials from various bills and issues from Holt's career, including the ERA, marital rape, wine laws, the lottery, juvenile justice, nursing, health education, mental retardation, archaeology, domestic violence, hospice, and the Holocaust. Other files relate to Holt's legislative career, including the North Carolina Legislative Women's Caucus; the State Council for Social Legislation; tribute dinners and awards; and other miscellaneous papers and letters.
  This is an unprocessed collection. Materials have not been arranged, and have only been refoldered as needed for access. Headings and folder titles were originally assigned by the creator, Bertha Holt.
  - Campaign materials, 1989-1990 (Box 1)
  - Nursing foundation (Box 1)
  - Backman, 1983 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence and newsletters, 1977-2000s (Box 1)
    Correspondence consists largely of thank-you notes and other fan mail. Folders with this material are labelled Orchids by the donor.
  - North Carolina wine laws, 1980s-2000s (Box 1)
  - Lottery, 1993-1994 (Box 1)
  - Marital rape (Laura X), 1980s-2000s (Box 1)
  - Ethics and campaign reforms, 1980s (Box 1)
  - Clippings, 1980s-1990s (Box 1)
  - ERA panel, 1980s (Box 1)
  - Obscenity study, 1980s (Box 1)
  - Women's history, 1990s (Box 1)
  - B's articles, 1970s (Box 1)
  - Juvenile justice, 2004 (Box 1)
  - Daily calendars, 1988 and 1990 (Box 2)
  - Health education/coordinators, 1980-1988 (Box 2)
  - Act to Regulate the Practice of Nursing, 1981 (Box 2)
  - White House conference, 1982 (Box 2)
  - Committee to Re-elect Bertha B Holt, 1990 (Box 2)
  - North Carolina Foundation for Nursing, 1990-1991 (Box 2)
  - Life Plan Trust Act/Community Trust (HB1000), 1991 (Box 2)
  - Wine Task Force; National Conference of State Legislators, 1993-1994 (Box 2)
  - Kennel Club, 1989 (Box 2)
  - State Council for Social Legislation, 1977-1981 (Box 2)
  - Queen's portrait, 1970s (Box 2)
  - Public hearing SB167, 8 April 1981 (Box 2)
  - North Carolina Council for Social Legislation, 1997 (Box 2)
  - Archaeology (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Association for Retarded Citizens, 1991 (Box 2)
  - North Carolina Legislative Women's Caucus, 1982-1994 (Box 3)
  - Tribute dinner for Bertha B Holt, 19 November 1999 (Box 3)
  - Letters when defeated, 1994 (Box 3)
  - Secrecy contract (Mavretic), 1989 (Box 3)
  - Domestic violence, 1993-1996 (Box 3)
  - Judicial District 17-A split, 1993 (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Woman of the Year, 1991 (Box 3)
  - Epilepsy, 1984 (Box 3)
  - Hospice, 1984 (Box 3)
  - Council on the Holocaust, 1989-1993 (Box 3)
  - Center for the American Woman and Politics (CAWP): Forum for Women and State Legislators, 1991 (Box 3)
  - News clippings, 1984-2003 (Box 3)
- Accession (2010-0104), 1970-2010, (2 boxes) (Box 3)
  Accession (2010-0104) (750 items; 1.3 lin. ft.; dated 1970-2010) includes clippings; correspondence; subject and research files from issues such as churches, seatbelt and school bus safety, welfare, gun control, and wine; committee materials, including the Science and Technology Board; a scrapbook from 1973-1979; and other miscellaneous materials.
  This is an unprocessed collection. Materials have not been arranged, and have only been refoldered as needed for access.
  - Clippings, 1975-2009 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1970-2010 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous, 1974-2010 (Box 4)
  - Science and Technology Board, 1981 (Box 4)
  - Rep. Holt's day planner, 1994 (Box 4)
  - Button, undated (Box 4)
  - Standing committees, 1974-1976 (Box 4)
  - Seatbelts on school buses, 1999-2000 (2 folders) (Box 4)
  - Church, 1970-1971 (Box 4)
  - Welfare and domestic violence, 1997 (Box 4)
  - Wine, 1979-1985 (Box 4)
  - Gun control, 1975-1977 (Box 4)
  - Scrapbook, Times to Remember, 1973-1979 (Box 5)
- Accession (2010-0192), 1940-2007, (1 box) (Box 5)
  Accession (2010-0192) (1125 items; 1.5 lin. ft.; dated 1940-2007) includes subject and research files from issues such as healthcare, education, crime, and prisons; materials from the Equal Rights Amendment; files from various events that Holt attended, including the Center for Creative Leadership, the White House Conference on Aging (1981), and files from her membership in the Women's Forum of North Carolina. Also contains materials from her Episcopal Church activities.
  - Negotiable Instruments Law notes, 1940-1941 (Box 6)
  - North Carolina Historical Almanack, 1964 (Box 6)
  - English-speaking Union, 1973 (Box 6)
  - Equal Rights Amendment, 1975-1981 (Box 6)
  - Episcopal Church correspondence and activities, 1975-2007 (2 folders) (Box 6)
  - Legislative Ethics, etc., 1979 and undated (Box 6)
  - White House Conference on Aging, 1981 (3 folders) (Box 6)
  - Center for Creative Leadership, 1989-1990 (Box 6)
  - Southern Legislative Conference, 1990 (Box 6)
  - The Law of the Land, Seminar on North Carolina Constitution, 1993 (Box 6)
  - Women's Forum of North Carolina, 1980s-2000s (3 folders) (Box 6)
  - North Carolina Council for Women, 1992-1995 (Box 6)
  - Democratic Women of North Carolina, undated (Box 6)
  - Clippings, general, 1976-1990 and undated (Box 6)
  - Clippings re: Bertha Holt, 1975-1993 (Box 6)
  - Subject files (Box 6)
    - Church and state (Box 6)
    - Crime and prisons (Box 6)
    - Healthcare (Box 6)
    - Education (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous, including alcohol, highway safety, handguns, contract workers, etc. (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, constituents, 1982-1998 and undated (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, conciliatory after Holt's election loss in 1994 (Box 6)
  - General Assembly, miscellaneous, 1985-1990 (Box 6)
  - Photographs (2), undated (Box 6)